It was Christmas time, December of 1993,
记得那是1993的圣诞节
and there I was, just about to turn seven years old,
我当时也就差不多七岁吧
and thoroughly transfixed by anything with a CPU inside it.
而且对任何有CPU的东西都十分感兴趣
And luckily, the household my family was visiting
幸运的是，我当时去开圣诞派对
for a Christmas party had a shiny new 486 in their office.
的人家书房里有台全新的486电脑
The guy who owned the computer was browsing
当时那位正在玩电脑的大哥正在浏览，并向我显摆
and showing off the latest games he had downloaded
from a local BBS, like Halloween Harry
从当地BBS下载的游戏，诸如Halloween Harry之类的
and other platformers.
Then something happened
然后那个改变我对游戏看法的事情就发生了
that changed my entire perception of video games.
I saw this.
我看到了这个
I specifically remember him opening the door,
我十分清晰地记得他打开了那扇门
shooting things until they collapsed in a bloody heap,
打着怪兽，直到它们倒在血泊中
and looking around at the green vats of slime,
然后看着周围的绿色毒河
all in an environment that felt entirely believable.
这个画面合在一处，让人难以置信
It was textured, it had lighting, it was 3D,
这玩意有纹理！这玩意有光照！这玩意是3D的！
and just then my dad walked into the room,
就在那时我老爹走进了屋子
saw the gory carnage,
看着屏幕上的血流漂橹
and thought "ehh maybe this game isn't made for little kids."
然后说：“额，这游戏小孩玩不合适吧。”
The dude on the computer apologized, shut it down,
那位玩电脑的大哥道了歉，把游戏关了
and let me play Commander Keen 4 instead.
然后就让我玩Commmander Keen 4
And while I was notably impressed by that as well,
当然这个游戏也挺耐人
I never forgot that other game
但我永远忘不了那个流着绿色毒河的游戏
with the green vats of slime.
The guns, the demons, that feeling of doom.
那些枪声不断，怪兽吓人，毁灭一切的场景
I thought about it every so often for years,
那游戏的画面几年来一直在我的脑海里挥之不去
those images burned into my brain.
并在我的心中留下了烙印
It was not until many years later
几年后，趁着那时P2P网络正火之时
in the days of peer-to-peer file sharing services
like Napster and Morpheus,
例如Napster和Morpheus
注：在中国是迅雷，QQ旋风等，吸着eMule和BitTorrent的血。
that I finally got to play it for myself.
我终于搞来了一份来玩
I found some shady executable for Doom 95
我当时下载了一份来路可疑的DOOM 95程序
and those memories came flooding back
然后当我第一次亲自玩第一章第一关时
as I played through E1M1 for the first time.
一个个鲜活的面容又在我眼前飞扬了起来
Yeah, I'd played games like Unreal and Thief at that point,
是的，我当时像个小偷一样的玩游戏，心里很虚
but Doom?
但是《毁灭战士》呢？
It was still able to get its hooks into me
它还是毫无疑问地把我给迷住了
with no problem at all.
The shooting, the music, the level design,
它射击的方式，它富有激情的BGM，它精巧的关卡设计
the way enemies consistently surprised me.
源源不断的地狱渣子让我印象深刻
It felt shockingly fresh, even though the game
就算当时游戏发行了八年，我玩起来还是觉得恐怖又新鲜
was eight years old at that point.
And now, with it approaching 23 years old
现在呢，这个游戏已经23岁了
and a new Doom looming on the horizon,
而且全新的《毁灭战士》又将发行了
it's finally time to discuss the one and only Doom,
现在终于是时候来谈论这独一无二的《毁灭战士》
here on LGR.
在我的LGR频道上
And yes, sometime later, I repented of my file sharing sins.
当然，在这之后，我也为我盗版玩游戏而后悔:-(
注：各位在网上听歌的，也许你听到的就是盗版，av711540711@Pig_Floyd
Here's my personal copy of the game,
这是我自己买的游戏拷贝
which came in this slim cardboard sleeve
装在这个超薄的纸盒中
directly from id Software.
直接从开发商id Software发货
Now, originally, Doom was a shareware game, meaning that
当然，最初的《毁灭战士》是个共享软件
注：共享软件是各种”先使用后付费“的软件，诸如WinRAR
there was a sizable chunk of it made available for free,
意味着你可以从很多中渠道搞到免费版本游戏
including the level I saw as a seven year old.
包括我七岁时看到的关卡
If you wanted the whole thing, and who didn't,
如果你想玩所有关卡的话，而且谁不想呢
you couldn't just go to a computer store and buy it,
你想当然地去电脑城买
you had to order it by phone or by mail.
你必须经由电话或者邮件去订购
And when you did, they'd send you this package.
当你订购完成后，你会收到个包裹
That's why there's no barcode or anything like that on here,
这就是为什么这上面没有条码之类的东西
it was never officially sold in stores,
这玩意从来就没有在商场里卖过
at least not in the U.S.A.
至少在美国是这样的
You just got this little box, the game on some floppy disks,
你只是搞来了这个小盒子，一堆装着游戏的磁盘
and a stapled together manual,
还有这装订好的游戏说明书，而且质量出奇的好:-)
which is of surprisingly decent quality.
However, that's not to say
当然，这也不代表在美国没卖过《毁灭战士》
that Doom was never, ever sold in American stores.
Now for one thing, the shareware version
顺便一提，这个免费版本
got all sorts of retail releases, including this one
倒是在市面上能见到，包括这个
that was bundled alongside GT Software distributed games
附带于其他GT Software发行的游戏中的，诸如德军总部3D
like Wolfenstein 3D.
The box looks a little more substantial
这个相比完整版的，看上去更加充实
than the official full version release,
but it's still just the shareware episode
但是里面仍然是免费版游戏，你在网上可以免费下载
that you could download for free.
It wasn't until 1995 with the release
直到1995年《毁灭战士终极版》的发行，商场架子上才看见完整版的游戏
of The Ultimate Doom, that store shelves were graced
with the full version's presence.
The box art may not be as impressive as the others,
也许盒子上的画没有别的游戏的吸引人
but it included all the original episodes,
但是它包括了原先完整版的所有关卡
plus an additional fourth episode,
而且还附带了第四章
and the latest patches, which made it an attractive option
还有最新的游戏补丁，这个让
for old and new players alike.
新老玩家都很喜欢
There were also a slew of add-on packs for Doom
之后还有一连串的毁灭战士附加包
like the omni-present D!Zone series of packs,
诸如omni-presentD!Zone系列附加包
which added all sorts of maps and custom content.
里面包括了一系列的地图和自制内容
Also worth mentioning for collectors
对于收藏家来说
is the Doom Collector's Edition, released in 2001.
这个2001年发行的《毁灭战士典藏版》也值得收藏
This has some pretty metal box art,
盒子设计得十分金属
and includes Final Doom, Ultimate Doom,
还包括了《最终毁灭战士》, 《终极毁灭战士》
and the sequel, Doom II.
以及续集，《毁灭战士二代》
But yeah, for the rest of the video,
当然，接下来的视频
I'll just be taking a look at Doom
我们只是来讨论原版《毁灭战士》
and The Ultimate Doom, because I mean, ugh.
以及《终极毁灭战士》，因为它们......
They make me moist.
它们使我感动至极
And I'll probably explode if I don't play them again soon.
要是我三天不碰，我估计又得踢坏太上老君的炼丹炉了:-P
Doom begins with this fantastic splash screen
《毁灭战士》由这个超级耐人的开屏动画开始
and some appropriate mood setting MIDI music
伴随着十分能调动情绪的MIDI音乐
by the magnificent, Maestro Bobby Prince.
由音乐大师Bobby Prince编曲
While a demo plays in the background,
当游戏演示在背景展示时
you're free to peruse the options,
你可以自由地浏览这些选项
look at registration information,
看一下授权情况
or start up a game and dive into the depths of Hell.
或者开局游戏，打入阴曹地府的核心B-)
And since Hell is quite nice this time of year,
鉴于现在地狱的各位都十分儒雅随和
I recommend choosing your difficulty and doing that.
我十分建议大家挑个合适难度来玩
Heh, and I always loved that nightmare difficulty
而且呢，我十分喜欢的噩梦难度（超级难的难度）
注：第一和第五个难度子弹加倍，但是第五个难度怪兽攻击性更强
我是个宝宝
简单点行吗
我准备好了
超级恐怖
噩梦到死
is brutally honest with you.
对你而言就很难了:-(
你确定要玩这个难度吗？
难道你很喜欢被虐吗？
（这个难度甚至没那么的公平）
It's unfair.
这对你可能不太公平
No complaints if you play it, it's your fault.
你要玩的话，出事别怪人哦:-|
Now I could very well talk about a hundred thousand topics
从现在开始我可以滔滔不绝地讨论关于毁灭战士的事情了
in regards to Doom from here forward.
The creation story of the game is fascinating,
这个游戏的幕后故事也十分有意思
the people behind its development are legendary,
开发游戏的大师们，个个都是传奇
the tale of how it played a huge part
它们在开发SRB时的巨大贡献十分有趣
in creating the SRB is interesting,
the idea that its level design and weapons selection
它们的关卡设计和武器设定
are the daddy of all FPS games,
是目前所有FPS游戏的基础
and the fact that the technical feats
还有不得不说的，在1993年超前的技术壮举
that this was pulling off in 1993
were like something from another world back then,
在当时就好象曹操看见袁绍营里吃着玉米
but because each of those topics
但鉴于上述细节都适合做个节目细谈
deserve a video of their own,
I just want to talk about the gameplay in general today
我今天只是来大概谈谈游戏的玩法
and how it makes me feel.
以及它给我的感受
Namely, there are a few things about Doom
当然，《毁灭战士》肯定有些特点
还不仅仅是“毁灭”哦...
that make it distinctly Doom
才让其称上”毁灭“二字
这可是
and nothing else has since compared.
而且在之前从来没有出现过
Well, other than Doom II, which is arguably the better game
当然，抛开《毁灭战士二代》，当然也是个好的续作
even though its more or less an add-on to this one,
尽管这个或多或少算是《毁灭战士》的DLC
but that, too, is for another video another time.
但是这个呢，还是回来再做个视频吧
Ugh, man, isn't Doom too great?
Emmm，难道二代不耐人吗？
The new enemies, the phenomenal levels,
全新的敌人，加强的武器
the super shotgun, ugh!
还有双管猎枪，啊！
Okay I'm sorry, I'm getting ahead of myself.
好吧，刚才失态，请见谅
Mmm.
一手的满足:-)
So what is it that makes Doom Doom?
那么是什么让《毁灭战士》担当得起“毁灭”二字呢？
Well for me, it's a combination of controls,
对于我来说，这是由控制方式
level design, pacing, weapons, and atmosphere.
关卡设计，关卡衔接（原意走步），武器，还有氛围来决定的
If any one of those were taken away,
要是缺少了一点的话
it would be another thing entirely.
那就是另一个特点了，甚至于另一种游戏了
Much like if you're mixing drinks
就像你认为林妹妹说话很扎人
注：原文意思是调饮料忘了最重要的调料，以至于这杯饮料不是你所想要的了
and leave out a key ingredient in one of them,
但是你忘了她的小姐身份
sure it's still more or less the same drink,
当然这还是个有血有肉的人物
but it's also different enough
但是和一开始想的完全不一样了
that you may as well get another name entirely.
这可能就是另一个人了，比如晴雯
With Doom, that cocktail of control over your character,
当你玩《毁灭战士》的时候，你会感到那种控制角色的快感
the layout, the features of each map,
整个游戏的界面，每张地图的各个机关
the expertly crafted speed and difficulty,
还有精心设计的速度和难度，这些感觉都杂糅在一起了
the enjoyable lethal array of guns,
令人愉悦的枪林弹雨
and the overall feeling of exploring each level,
还有探索每一关时的无所适从和提心吊胆
all of these come together in a way
这些感觉的集合
that makes Doom distinct,
造就了这个游戏的“毁灭特色”
and in my opinion is where the so-called Doom clones
在我看来，这也就让那些90年代中期
of the mid-90s frequently fell short.
流行的类《毁灭战士》游戏都黯然失色
When you're controlling Doom guy,
当你在控制毁灭战士这个人的时候
as he is so creatively called,
大家都喜欢这么叫它
everything feels like it's in its place,
很多事情看起来都各归其位
like it has a purpose and nothing is extraneous.
好像什么东西都是有前因后果，而不是外来的
There's an intimate sense of connection
看上去他好像与你的双手
between your hands, the hardware,
你的硬件，和屏幕上
and what's happening on screen.
的一举一动都有很紧密的关系
It's like your keyboard and mouse transform
就好像你的键盘和鼠标都穿越到游戏中
into a piece of finely tuned weaponry,
变成了上膛的武器
one that's more than capable of wiping out
而且十分适合将地狱大军
the entirety of Hell's forces, if you're skilled enough.
都给揍回他的老巢，只要你技巧足够熟练的话
And you know, just when you think you've got the hang of it,
而且你也知道，当你认为你解决得差不多时
repetition gives way to surprise,
重复杀戮就变成了惊喜杀戮
as something you forgot was there catches you off guard,
因为一点疏忽就能让你喝上一壶的了
or something you didn't know was there kills you.
或者你没看见的敌人正在磨你的血:-(
This leads right into the level design
这就是精巧的关卡设计所带来的好处
which seems kind of nonsensical at first glance.
第一眼看上去有点无厘头
I mean this is supposed to be a space military base
我的意思是说，这本应是个太空军事基地
注：UAC=Union Aerospace Corporation 联合太空技术集团
for the most part, and if that's the case,
至少大部分区域都是这样的，真是如此的话
they oughta fire their architect.
为啥不一把火给烧了呢:-P
The number of dead ends, labyrinths, and secret doors
杀掉的敌人数目，迷宫和秘密的门
is downright bizarre in that respect.
这些从头到尾都是无厘头的
But what it lacks in logical believability,
尽管这游戏细想想真是扯淡
it makes up for in pure fun.
玩起来还是十分刺激的:-D
Over two decades later, and the levels hold up in ways
谁能想到20年后，这些设计精巧的
that surprised me even more on playing through it again.
关卡依然能让我惊奇不已，玩味不止
It's a web of carefully constructed switches,
各个关卡本身就是开关
windows, doors, passageways,
窗户，大门，过道
secret areas, and floor toggles.
秘密区域和楼梯开关的集合
And while each one is placed with an explicit purpose,
然后当每一个机关都各居其所时
not all of them are there
玩家们又不一定非得把它们都过一遍
for every player on every play through.
Sometimes you want to do a speed run,
有时你想速战速决
sometimes you want to take it slow,
有时你想驻足厮杀
other times you just want to search for secrets,
当然，你只是想搜索秘密地带
and beyond that you may want to go for a new record
更有甚者，你只是想在捡完所有物品，
in terms of items grabbed and enemies slaughtered.
杀掉所有敌人的情况下，看看自己是不是破了记录
100 percenting the game is something I've never done,
集齐这个游戏所有关卡的的三个100%，我好像永远完不成
注：KILLS 杀戮，ITEMS 物品，SECRETS 秘密地带
but the manner in which these levels are constructed
但是这些关卡精巧的设定
makes me long to pull it off someday.
也让我能一直很高兴地卡在这一关
And then seeing spots where Doom isn't afraid
然后看看那些能把
to do something crazy to the player,
毁灭战士给吓死的地方
like tossing them into a strobe-lit dark room
例如走进了一闪一闪昏暗的屋子
or instantly dropping them into a pit of demons,
或者很快就掉进装满了魔鬼的坑
because they stepped on the wrong floor tile,
因为他走进了错误的楼梯:-(
makes me yearn for more first person shooters like this
这些都更让我对这种主动吓人的第一人称射击游戏更加喜欢
that didn't bother coddling you.
Speaking of which, the pacing of the game keeps you on edge
说到这个，这个游戏的节奏
throughout the entire campaign.
自始至终都是一样的逼人甚紧
From E1M1 onward, you're greeted with a game
从第一章第一关开始，你所面对的是
that's simple to control, yet wickedly fast
易于操控，然而却是邪恶的快节奏
and unafraid to dole out the pain.
并毫不畏惧地向你抛出痛苦
Doom goes balls out in the way it tosses demons at you,
这个游戏会源源不断地向你抛出一个个狼与豺
often from within areas that have since been termed
经常是从你拿完东西后从哪堵墙后面
monster closets, and if you can't see them,
突然冒出来的:-(，如果你看不见它们的话
you can hear them, and that compels you to move forward.
你可以听见它们的狂吟，而这些迫使你继续走下去
To put it simply, if there's demons,
简单来说，怪物多的地方
you're probably going the right way.
八成就是准道儿了
And each enemy is designed in such a way
而且每一种怪兽都是按照
that directly counters the moves and weapons
能用你目前能得到的
you've gained thus far.
武器所能解决掉的路子来设计的
Some feature hit-scan weapons, others utilize projectiles
有些怪兽有连击武器，有些怪兽你可以躲过
that can be dodged.
Several will chew your face off if you're too close,
有些怪物呢呢，当你离它很近时，受到的伤害会很大
and others will compel you to use your most powerful weapons
有些腻味人的会迫使你用最强力的武器
even if you're running low on ammo
就算你弹量不足
and probably should be saving up for later.
而且你也想在后面的战斗中节省些
But man, how hard is it to save up
但是老弟啊，要是你也有一堆美式装备
when the weapons are this good anyway?
你难道还会精打细算吗？
Doom builds on the formula set forth
《毁灭战士》和《德军总部3D》在许多方面的设计语言是相似的
in Wolfenstein 3D in so many ways,
then bumps it up so many notches
然后在此基础上提升很多，甚至比前者不知道高到哪里去了
that it's hard to even compare the two.
Yet it's easy to lose sight of how legendary it is,
但是大家还是没能意识到这个游戏的经典之处
seeing as practically first person shooter from here onward
只是片面地认为它是第一人称射击游戏的开山制作
has aped the basic Doom load-out to some degree.
某种程度上给《毁灭战士》造成影响（没看懂，有懂的弹幕覆盖）
Punching for basic melee, a chainsaw for ballsy risktakers,
用拳头来打群架，拿锯子砍掉那腻味人的
a pistol for when you're low on everything else,
实在啥都没有的话，用手枪应急
a shotgun because taking down multiple enemies is great,
用猎枪来个一枪多头
a chain-gun that puts the pistol ammo to good use,
用机关枪来充分利用手枪子弹
a rocket launcher for blowing things up including yourself,
用火箭发射器来轰掉一切，包括自己
a plasma gun for tearing through enemies at a rapid rate,
用等离子枪来灭掉能跑过记者的怪物
and the one and only BFG 9000,
当然，我们无法忘怀那唯一的BFG 9000
the biggest [bleep] gun indeed!
又大(big)又＊*（fxxking）的终极武器！
Jensen Huang: 3090 is a beast, a ferocious GPU, a BFGPU
Every one of these is a skillfully crafted tool
每件武器都是精心设计的
for dispatching violent justice on the Hell spawn
用来在地狱里用血和子弹
that roam the once hallowed halls
宣扬我们人类暴力的一面，消灭它们的母巢
of wherever the hell this is.
正如它们玷污我们的神庙一样，并且把地狱翻个底朝天
Once you figure out how to best use each gun,
当你搞明白如何正确使用每一种枪时
the fun never ends because you know
杀戮的快感就永不停歇，因为你明白
that there's a proper time and place for every one of them,
这就是这种武器在这个场合下的使命
and usually that place is dark, horrific,
一般来说，这种地方是十分黑暗，恐怖的
and downright delicious in its brooding sci-fi atmosphere.
正中这个游戏阴暗的科幻气氛
The aesthetic of Doom is timeless if you ask me.
而这就是这个游戏在审美方面的成就
That happy little side effect of the game engine
这个游戏引擎一个比较好的方面是
where everything was dark in the distance,
黑暗部分在很远就能看见
it's arguably the single most important thing
这个在《毁灭战士》塑造形象方面
for giving Doom its distinctive look.
显然是十分重要的
Darkness is everywhere,
黑暗无处不在
only a few steps away.
也许就在几步之外
Even in what appeared to be brightly lit rooms.
就算在看上去都是很亮的屋子里
There is no hiding from it
总会有什么东西藏在墙的后面
and it will probably tear your soul
而且会很快地把你的魂儿吓出来，并剁成齑粉:-(
from your mortal form in no time,
unless you've got your trusty boom stick on hand
除非你紧紧地握着你最信赖的武器
and in that case, keep the finger on the trigger
所以以防万一，按住扳机，别让它跑了
and do not let go.
Whether you're scouting out science facilities
无论你是在探索科学基地
or meandering around the halls of the damned,
或是下了十八层地狱
Doom's levels ooze style of the most dreadful variety.
《毁灭战士》怪异的关卡中流露出一股可怕的气息
Yet, it's not as dark as its software's next game, Quake,
当然，这个没有这个公司出的下一款游戏《雷神之锤》黑暗
it's still got that bright dash
这个游戏还是到处还是充满着鲜艳的像素和贴色彩
of delightfully pixelated color here and there.
If only to remind you that what you're fighting for
如果你能明白你在干什么的话
is probably worth it, and it's the early 90s.
这个游戏很适合你，而且这可是90年代早期出品的啊
Bright colors are still cool in video games.
鲜艳的颜色仍然在游戏界流行
And every so often, you'll run into something
而且或多或少，你在遇到某些难过的机关时
that the devout of the time took much offense to.
你都得十分专心地解决它们
Upside down crosses, pentagrams,
倒五角星啊，神秘五角星啊
images of demons and various other bits of Satanic imagery
恶魔的图片和一堆其他的撒旦图片
that really nailed down the fact
这也更加显示出
that Doom is pretty freaking metal.
《毁灭战士》十分金属的内核
I'm not just talking about the design of things either,
当然，我说到不是设计还是啥的
I'm talking about that stellar soundtrack by Bobby Prince.
我说到是Bobby Prince编的游戏音乐
Sure, much of it mimics the songs of Metallica, Pantera,
当然，这些配乐大多受 Metallica, Pantera,
注：E1M8（第一章的最后一关）配乐的riff改编自 King Crimson 的 Starless
Slayer, and Judas Priest, but I say bring it on!
Slayer 和 Judas Priest 的影响，但是要我说，上劲就行！
This is a game that was clearly made by
这些游戏显然是由
100% all natural geeks fueled by copious metal albums,
100%纯极客在金属音乐的薰陶
soft drinks, leftover pizza, and D&D campaigns.
汽水和外卖披萨的满足和恐怖派对游戏的刺激下完成的
Doom is an interactive monument
《毁灭战士》很明显是90年代早期西方流行文化
to early 90s popular culture and more specifically,
的生动体现，主要是
the culture of dorks who just like the sound of hard rock
那堆只想着听着重金属摇头
and the sight of blood and guts on a computer screen,
看着屏幕上血肉飞溅的小年轻们
my kind of people.
没错，就是我们这样的人B-)
But beyond how enjoyable it is to play,
但是咱先抛开玩游戏的快感
how influential it was on gaming,
它在游戏史上的地位
and how unique it was to stick in my mind
以及它自我小时候以来给我的印象来接着说
for all those years as a kid,
Doom is about much more than that.
《毁灭战士》可不止这些
Doom is all about its community.
《毁灭战士》有自己的圈子
The culture of creativity that this game inspired
由这个游戏引出的创造力和同人也造就了这个游戏的传奇
is the stuff of legend.
And the crazy thing is
更令人疯狂的是，官方都没有发行过创造工具
it wasn't even released with modding tools,
yet immediately after the release of the shareware episode,
就在免费版本游戏发行后不长时间
players of the game got to work on creating utilities
硬核玩家们就努力开发工具，让人们随意修改游戏，各显神通
that allowed users to mod the game
into practically whatever they wanted.
Chances are, If you've given much of your time
万事俱备，你只要有足够的时间
to Doom at all,
you've given some time to trying out
你就可以装几个玩玩
or making your own custom WAD.
或者自己定制WAD（Doom游戏引擎数据文件）
Simpsons Doom, Star Wars Doom, Back to Saturn X,
Kill Barney, on and on and on and on,
Kill Barney, 还有很多很多......
and to this day, there are still tons of them being made.
而且直到现在，还在有人做呢
Not only that, but source ports, total conversions,
不仅这些，还有源码修改，在线对话
注：DOOM引擎（idTech 1）Linux版在1997-12-23开源，github id-Software/DOOM
and modding overhauls, have transformed Doom
和深入定制，这些都把《毁灭战士》
into things that are absolutely mindblowing.
变成了十分烧脑的橡皮泥
Not to mention met with mainstream success,
当然它在主流市场的成功就更不必说了
who hasn't heard of Brutal Doom at this point, you know?
毕竟有谁没听说过Brutal Doom（十分著名的DOOM Mod）呢？
And it's not just the excellent single-player
而且你不仅可以和别人一起为单人游戏搞Mod
that got so many people modding the game either,
it was the included multiplayer modes.
这个游戏还有多人游戏模式
These not only let several players
这个不仅可以让梁山一百单八将们一起打战役
go through the entire campaign cooperatively,
but they could also compete
而且还可以在Deathmatch（死亡游戏）中来个三国并立
in what the game called deathmatch.
Yep, you've got Doom to thank for cementing the popularity
是的，你得感谢《毁灭战士》的多人游戏流行
of this mode that is still incredibly popular
才让现在的多人射击游戏
in multiplayer shooters to this day.
能够继续流行，并不断壮大
It's a testament to Doom's original gameplay
是啊，《毁灭战士》奠基下的游戏方式
that got people that enthusiastic about it.
让人们对此是如此的欲罢不能
So much so, that their enthusiasm
如此下去，它们的兴趣与激情
turned into a rich creative outlet.
就转化为了无尽的创造力
And seeing as that outlet has turned many a modder
然后这无尽的创造力就让一个个写Mod的人
into a professional game developer,
进化为专业的游戏开发者
the influence Doom has had is, well it's hard to fathom.
《毁灭战士》的影响可真是......难以估量了
And that's why I have to talk about it
这也就是为什么我现在一直在谈论它
and will be talking about it for years in the future.
而且在将来还会一直谈论它
However Doom 2016 turns out, well frankly I don't care.
然而Doom 2016版发行了，说真的，我对此并不太上心
注：2016年5月13日在Steam上发行
I'll play it, I hope I enjoy it, but either way
我当然会玩它，并好好享受它，但是抛开这个
it doesn't change how I'll feel about all I've just said
它不会改变我刚才说到的，我对这个游戏的感情
in this video.
Regardless of where Doom's legacy ends up
不管《毁灭战士》系列在Bethesda（发行商）手里会变得怎样
in Bethesda's hands,
it's the original Doom games that still have my heart.
原版《毁灭战士》游戏永远在我的心中有一席之地
Or more aptly, my soul.
更准确地说，是我的心中:-)
结束
结束了吗？
本视频由SuperBart翻译，原作者LGR发布于2016-5-13